so we're recording now
and um it looks like just three of us
and what i might do is outline
the the i suppose the background and the
structure
that i had thought might work initially
um which was
um so me being
from the awakening from the discord
awakening from the median crisis discord
server
i am keen to practice what
uh john viveki is calling dear logos
the logos the idea that
um two of us or three of us or you know
the right amount of people when we come
together in good faith
that something emerges out of the
dialectic
i think he calls it so the way that we
talk in good faith to one another that
none of us could have produced on our
own
and that that is inherently good
and a good deal logos will result in
wisdom
which is the highest good
[Laughter]
good thinking yeah so um
and of course um this was with respect
to
simon's contribution to the discord
server
[Music]
vis-a-vis quakerism and collective
presence
so i had kind of a structure about a
couple of questions to get us into that
but um since it's just the three of us i
i've got no kind of
uh claims to be running this so
so is there some something you'd like to
see
different to that before i sort of do my
bit
nothing yeah i think that's that's
pretty cool and uh i really don't know
anything about
quakerism except just the superficial
stuff and
and so yeah i'm just willing to learn
right now
beautiful and so i'm in perhaps um uh
for the recording
um shall i do a little introduction of
you or do you want to introduce yourself
uh i mean i'm yeah sure i can introduce
myself
oh no no sorry for simon no no no for me
okay great oh yeah okay well oh yeah
why didn't you why did you follow it
again
if you if you'd like to introduce what
you have picked up and then i'll add
any important bits i would love to
i would love to um so
my initial interest in talking to you
was
with regards to i suppose something that
isn't so public
for you as such something that you'd
find on your web page easily which is
quakerism but in the course of following
that up
um what i've learned about you is that
you're a
professor i believe that's right you've
got a phd
you've got a phd no professor yeah yeah
that means you're a doctor
a doctor of theory
okay and and that's computer science
it was it was a mixture of computer
science and psychology
uh cognitive science in fact uh the same
area as john vicki actually but
um yeah earlier than him and uh
probably not the same area but uh the
same
field of study brilliant
um and part of your practice
post your successful
phd was to found a
an organization called cetus
c test we call it yeah cetus which seems
to be a sort of
working at the confluence of technology
learning
[Music]
and as far as i could see it human
computer interaction
being your specialty and how that kind
of
uh unfolds its way into cognition is
that a fear
let me let me put that in a bit of
perspective um cetis was founded a long
long but
long long time before i came on the
scene
i just helped it move from being part of
the university set up
into its own worker co-op structure
cetus is mainly a it's a it's an
educational technology consultancy
um and it's it's mainly these days to do
with um
more uh data analytics and
um things like that but it's also it's
always been interested in
standardization
and um standards open standards being
the way to coordinate
um people in the technology world
and um the important thing
i think for me is the standardization
process
is fundamentally a consensus one
uh when you set up a standard of any
sort technical standard
you have to well there is no
you have no power over anybody you have
to get people to agree
and in order to get people agree you
have to understand them
you have to listen you have to
understand their language what they're
talking about and you have to be able to
translate between the different
languages
so that's the real interest for me
oh that's beautiful now i'm going to
come back to that
and do first of all that kind of
inclusive open
standard thing by just quickly following
up with solid
and then i'm going to ask some questions
okay so
did you want to introduce yourself and
let us know about you because
part of part of what i'm interested in
is building a bit of
community here too oh yeah
well the thing is i really don't know i
don't i don't think i can add much to
the conversation about a
you know quakerism and collective
princessing so i'm not sure
it's any useful real that's fine then
but yeah
so i would be interested to hear where
i'd be very interested to hear where
you're coming from what's your
background and how you how you're
approaching this basically
well uh i've been i don't know i've been
just interested in uh
you know peterson and jung and viveki
for like a couple years now
and uh the end philosophy in general
thanks to verveiki mostly
i've been reading up on my philosophy so
so yeah
okay that's good okay
useful style thank you oh well good well
okay well then i might proceed down the
path a little bit
and obviously solid if something strikes
you just jump in
yeah okay great so
um just quickly uh
simon about do you prefer simon or dr
grant
simon one of the things you might know
about quakers is that quakers abdurah
titles
because quakers like
quakers really dislike honorifics and
they um
they they like to treat people equally
irrespective of their social status and
that's one of the reasons why
they don't use honorific titles like mr
or mrs
or even doctor but if but doctor is
better than mr mister but uh
preferably not at all preferably simon
is just absolutely fine
well that's great i mean that not only
answers my question but tells us
something about what we're talking about
as well so um
i i have uh researched a little bit
into quakerism in preparation for our
discussion which is very interesting i
think i
i'm like quite a lot of people in that
quakerism has a kind of um
a liminal um appearance
in the consciousness sort of like oh
it's there and i'll get to it at some
stage however uh
there isn't a proper focus um and you
know i noticed
when you joined in a conversation how
respectful you were of
what other people were saying it was
obviously
um i don't know i'm not sure what the
word is it was obviously
in the right spirit even though you
weren't um
necessarily spending all the time in the
world there
and i at the same time was looking for
some way to contribute so i wanted to
learn more about
quakerism as well and
you also brought in collective presence
in which is uh
uh spiritual practice unless i'm
mistaken which is um
or wouldn't call it spiritual practice
but yes it's it's uh
i would leave out the word spiritual
right
so do you want to maybe just unfold a
piece about quakerism
and collective presenting uh or
do you prefer a few questions how would
you like to do it
okay i'll give a little introduction
then um i
came across quakerism firstly in my
student years um
[Music]
uh and actually i discovered later it's
curious so i discovered later that the
cradle of quaker is actually quite
simon your audio just cut out but i
think
you were just saying
no i can't hear that soul
okay that's much better oh yeah yeah
the jiggle i have to jiggle the jack
plug is that okay now that's good
i think we got you uh just up to the
point where uh
you were saying that you lived near the
cradle of quakerism which i think is
like
something like that
it's it's uh well lancaster is where i
am just physically at the moment
and um george fox went up
to this region northwest of england
and that's where that's where he found
the first band of people that founded
quakerism
the appeal of quakerism when i was a
student was that it has no creed
it has no paid ministers
and there's a lot of this feeling of
equality
and um and the lack of hierarchy that's
the important thing
and that really spoke spoke to me
um because having been
aware of the general position of
churches
um one thing i was keen to get beyond is
the sort of hierarchical
approach of you know the person on top
knows best and you know
we all follow kind of thing yeah
quakerism has always been a religion
where um well it is christian
fundamentally george fox was profoundly
christian although some people have now
gone beyond that and there are even some
non-theists which i think you would like
to bring in later
um but quakerism has always been a um
a practice where um
basically everybody has access to
the truth the inner light as it's called
and um what happens in uh there's no
liturgy
either in other words uh on sunday
mornings which is a bit of
throwback to tradition but on sunday
mornings quakers gather
uh for a meeting for worship and the
meeting for worship is entirely
unstructured
and sometimes the meeting for worship is
entirely silent
sometimes nothing is said at all more
likely
during meeting for worship somebody will
feel
a call to as we say minister they will
stand
up they will say something
which they feel they're led to say and
then they will sit down again
nobody will comment or on that nobody
will reply
to that directly nobody will
question it but they might add their own
ministry later so it's a very very
open practice um now
when i met um ria who's also just
recently been active on the um
uh on this in this area the store and
also um john vivek's
things um from flanders um
she had been writing this book uh
collective presencing
an emerging human capacity and um
i thought this looks really interesting
i thought so
at the time it was um it was just in a
series of blog posts on wordpress so i
thought nah
let's put it into one piece so i put it
into one piece so i could read it better
and that
proved to prove to be very useful and so
that's what the book of the book that
you see today
um a lot along with a lot of other
tiding up
but i noticed that when i read into the
collective presence saying
um practice
[Music]
although the approach to collective
presence
is completely different and not at all
religious
what they end up with um
is something which felt
to me very like quaker practice
in other words people in a circle
um not speaking from that ego
um but reaching for something collective
uh the subtitle what's possible when
people are when people are truly
presence together
and true presence together is
um is what quakers also aim for
um quakers we call it the presence in
the midst
and ria called it the magic in the
middle and i thought hang on that's the
same thing
even though it comes from a completely
different perspective
so that was really
the barest outline of the quaker
practice and how i connected with
collect collective presence things so
over to you to ask more questions on
that
yeah that's terrific in my own notes
one of the themes that came out was this
idea of light
in quakerism um
and you know i have a christian
background i am christian
and i think one of the surprising things
i learned simon was that
as you indicated earlier that
quakerism isn't necessarily christian
now
as such
it all depends by christian and that is
a big question
yeah yeah uh and it's not a leading uh
thing i'm just
pointing out to me it was surprising
because
that's one of the things that unfolded
as i went along one of my sources by the
way was
on youtube a channel called quaker speak
which you probably know about
i i don't i don't know that it's
interesting i don't know
well i i gather that it's probably
american
around pennsylvania where a lot of the
quakers no doubt
yeah yeah and no there was a muslim
quaker
um
and others and they they sort of
carefully made that distinction but you
know i think your history was
very much um
[Music]
coming out of christianity as far as i
could see
so that that concept of light is
something that
struck me no pun intended
you know so is it specifically innovate
well that's the way it comes that's why
it's spoken of in in amongst quakers
usually yes in the sense that it's the
light which is present
which is present within everyone
that of god which is often
is often the phrase which is used that's
of god in everyone
right so um basically
the quaker principle is that you know
there is the
seed in everyone it's just a question of
how do you
reach it how how do you make a present
how do you bring it out
so in other words we don't need somebody
else's light is the important thing
another person's light
there is the light within us within each
one of us
so um and other other people have said
you know the
inner teacher for example is another
another
um and yet even though it's inward
it's not purely of of the ego it's not
of the self
it's actually from
[Music]
the spirit and the spirit i think is
interpreted in
in a way which is very compatible by the
christian um
group you know the the the spirit
and the spirit i mean goodness me
there's
been enough theology written about what
is the holy spirit
um a very mysterious concept i think but
so that's what i think quakers
focus on yeah
i love that you know what you're saying
about separating the ego from the spirit
it makes me wonder if a large part of
your practice has to do with
that quietness is
is the practice of separating your ego
from
what else it could be emerging
yes i think i think ideally in in quaker
practice and quaker meeting for worship
you still
the mind quieten the mind and
fundamentally you open yourself you open
yourself
to what is coming
and you know it's both outward and
inward you open yourself to what is
there
but then you know that is comes through
yourself it does not come necessarily
through well it doesn't come through
authority it can equally come from
somebody else's ministry and somebody
else's ministry
can you say oh yes that speaks to my
condition you can
people people say people have said in
the past you know yes that
there's a surprising i think what people
feel so often
in in a really gathered quaker meeting
is another word which is used very often
in a very gathered quaker meeting people
notice that when somebody speaks
stands up and speaks what they say is
somehow
either very relevant to their own
condition or somehow
it's something that they might have said
themselves so there's a kind of
there's this sort of um
resonance if you like one way of putting
it
in the sen and the sense that we are all
in touch with this
common presence in the middle
that's amazing it makes me think of
tuning in
tuning into something something other
than
that each individual maybe
i mean from the christian perspective
you can just say tuning into the spirit
good enough yeah look to be honest with
you
in my ignorance um quakers
and shakers and puritans
and as i was learning researching for
these dunkers
and various uh various
um you know groups formed out of that
kind of
english civil war which is i think where
a lot of stem from
um to me in my ignorance i always
thought
okay this is just uh christians who were
shaking off again there's a pun but
unintended
they were kind of shaking off that kind
of uh
immensely uh dominating church and state
presence england in particular must have
been incredibly overbearing
and availing themselves of
perhaps what they saw in the scriptures
through people like george fox and those
sort
sorts of people who i i guess at the
time were showing a lot of courage
um and so the
yeah again through through my eyes i was
thinking of course you know they're
quaking
because they're going after this
experience
so not because uh
a clergyman told me chapter and verse
this is what the truth is but rather no
i want to have a touch of something real
myself beyond myself you know i want to
taste it
[Music]
and the consequence of that i imagined
was oh you know people are shaking and
all sorts of stuff
i don't know is that wrong
hmm
what is the consequence what is the
consequence that we're looking for
is that a real question that's all right
uh there's a real
question a real question i mean what
what what
and i think we can take that on two
levels what is what does an individual
look for
when they're looking for religion or
religious experience
and secondly what do we hope
that religion is going to how do we hope
that religion is going to function in
in society so what is the point of
religion
right
oh okay so that is a proper question
and um what are people seeking when they
uh engage with religion is that a fair
way of restating it
yeah and you know i can ask that to both
of you yeah what are you looking for
what do you what do you look for from
what might you get you're not
necessarily the religion is the only
place to get it from but
what kind of things are you looking for
when you engage with
religion well not to be uh
cheeky but i think out of respect for
the quaker style i'll let solid
answer first and i'll come after you
well it seems to me when uh when i just
have a
brief overview of all the different
religions what what's the
the consistent point seems to be like
something like
uh just quieting the ego and letting
yeah the spirit and just because our god
taking place you know like august and
saint augustine said
i i obey more to god than to myself i
think that's really what
people are looking for into religion and
which i guess they they missed a lot of
the time
because it's such a hard use task
what what's the problem for you in just
following your ego
why would that not be a good why would
that not feel right to you
personally
well i i guess it's just too limiting
you know you're not just not connected
enough to
to the rest of the world or just you're
just
being identified with the ego so
are you saying that there's a sense of
you're aware of
potential of connection which you don't
get just by focusing
in inside yourself purely yeah okay how
about you then julian
so
i think the
in thinking about the answer
there's sort of two levels of it for me
and
one level of it the deeper level
which came second was that
without the idea of
god and and that's my best word for it
god without the idea of god
it's all meaningless
in literally for me that is you know i
know that's not true for everybody
but for me it's all pointless
and that's that's operating at a level
within myself
that is beyond intellectual
that sense my second
answer to the question was really about
that as well which is
and this is where i think john vivek is
very helpful
for me in the culture in which i grew up
um meaning was to be found in
um intellectual apprehension
and so that kind of
pro-scientific
conception where oh it's only just a
matter of time before you
understand and then you'll get it and if
you don't get it well then you're done
and all of the associated pathologies
with that con
that that structure um
seemed absurd to me and for me
seeking a religion was a way to break
out of that
even if i found it absurd myself
in the secret what did you find absurd
the uh so to quote ken wilbur
what i found absurd initially was the
trans-rational
nature of seeking
[Music]
a truly transcendental experience
so i just qualify that really
quickly by saying he makes a very good
point ken wilber
the integral theory guy which is we
often make the mistake of saying
something's either uh pre-rational
or it's uh irrational but we're
forgetting this really important space
in in between because i think that which
we're talking about and the
trans-rational mm-hmm
as if rational was the only thing and of
course we know that it
that that can't be because rationality
itself is based on
yeah it's it's not as simple as that at
all yeah
good good
so when you look at um
what what's can you tell me a bit more
about about your
uh your christian uh faith julian and
how that how that works for you
sure um
i have to hold myself to account when
i'm talking to you about this
um because i'm i'm conscious that
in this whole experience uh in this
world that we're living in now where i
get to talk to you and soul ed and
you're on the other side of the world
[Music]
there's the pandemic on and there's all
sorts of stuff um
uh that the world is is awash in
to quote john viveki again
uh and that includes myself and so
one of the things with the christianity
is that i have to
hold myself to account for that in
myself as much as anything else
so excuse me if i get a little bit
emotional at times when i talk about
what
christianity means to me because to me
it's a sacred thing that that's not
to say that i'm right by the way i'm
supremely conscious about
that i'm not right um and the closer i
draw into what's sacred about it
for me the more immediately i'm
impressed with that
um so the
the the biographical side of my
christianity is that i grew up singing
in a um
in a uh high anglican cathedral
in uh in melbourne
st paul's cathedral yeah
um i haven't been there yeah look
all right yeah i i did notice simon your
your interest in music and um on your
channel and so on um
you can relate to that um yeah look um
i i i uh got a scholarship
um thanks to my mum and my dad they
pointed out you know if you get into
this choir you get a scholarship to a
good school
there was a workload so every day after
school from about the age of
uh eight years old uh till 15
uh every day except for saturday i would
go to the cathedral and we would
practice and we would do
what's called even song for half an hour
and uh all of that was happening
at the same time as some trouble in my
own little family
and uh you know um
over the years i found that that
that choir became home for me
at times when things weren't making
sense
and you know i had a few intriguing
experiences as you do you know um you
hear
you hear the bible preached you're
mostly ignoring it
like every other kid but
yeah if if you're feeling particularly
vulnerable or down at
a certain time and you hear some of the
words it gets through
and i remember comparing and contrasting
when i was younger and going that makes
sense to me
um for some reason simon one of the
things that comes up when i say that
is um the parable of the sower
right you know i just remember hearing
that um
and thinking well that's what you know
that's wise
and i want to be like that
as time went on um you know there's a
lot of ritual involved in that kind of
church
and eventually i became the head
chorister
so it was very hierarchical very
hierarchical
and i wasn't uh expecting that
it came when i was around about 13 years
old or something like that
and that was a profound experience for
me
it changed my life i would uh
be called on at the end of every service
to stand up in front of all the boys
and you know say a prayer or something
like that
and address what was going on one of the
things that jumped
out is that you know one of the boys was
yeah it's emotional talking about it but
one of the boys was
getting picked up and i remember
being i felt an urge to defend him
from where i was standing and it turned
out that that was a powerful thing for
him
uh and you know his mom me i think and
i remember looking at my what was going
on in my own life and um
there was a lot of sort of chaotic
feeling going on and
and seeing what was happening there and
just being so
very very conscious that most of this
was not to do with me
because i felt especially unworthy at
that time
especially i'm worthy and yet uh
well you can see where the sacredness
comes from there's an emotional tie i'll
never get rid off
so that's my early story about it
there's much more to tell but i don't
want to
hog the um but thank you for the
question
um may i ask you a question back
please i was interested to know
um in your
seeking um is that the right word i'm
sorry you go to a meeting
you're quiet and you're listening that
practice is
is it called seeking i can't remember
no not particularly um
just i don't know
in meeting for worship yeah gathered
yeah just got a meeting for worship yes
have you had um
[Music]
experiences which for you
were something you'd be willing to share
that's not too personal but that
were profound in that
in that sense of what you've asked the
question about what's
what's religion for and so on
i wouldn't say i've had any kind of you
know religious
experiences in the in the way that some
people talk about them sort of like you
know
overwhelming kind of
ecstatic experiences or transcendental
experiences
um
i think my experience in meeting for
worship
is of being present and being in touch
and
um
allowing the inner light allowing the
conscience allowing
uh allowing the spirit to
listen listening basically to what is
there which whatever you call it
i have been impressed as i say sometimes
with
the way that occasionally not not every
not a very common experience but i've
been impressed by how
what other people say speaks to me
and i think sometimes you know the
experience of
having something to say of being given
something to say
is quite
[Music]
um
i'm not sure what the word is um
[Music]
quite humbling and also quite powerful
you know like
i've got i have to get up and say this
um
i don't really know what words to use
and maybe i go over some things in my
mind and maybe something gels and
something doesn't do i think
okay and then you
wait for the right moment and you think
okay
now there is this urge get up and say
this
that's quite a profound experience
however it happens
i think afterwards sometimes
it's not it's not by by no means
universal but sometimes
after meeting for worship when you're
having refreshments or whatever
and just chatting people sometimes come
up to you or i sometimes come to
somebody else and say
thank you for that ministry it really
spoke to me and it does
sometimes
i don't think my
religious experience is it's it's not a
sort of
fancy flashy one you know of of of
that kind of um uh
it's it's not psychedelic it's not kind
of transcendental in that
sense it's more
just getting in touch with
reality and and allowing oneself
sometimes to hold a mirror up and say
you know what am i doing is this
in silence there's no escape from your
conscience
um i think
we escape a lot most people escape a lot
by distracting themselves by social
media maybe
or as it was television and now it's
social media
um there's great power and silence in
it some phrase that you used earlier
julian a whole holding holding me to
account
and i think that's that's a lot of it is
you're you're letting
[Music]
whatever process it is work inside you
to connect
things up to allow in
what you too often shut out
um to allow in
you know to to allow truth i suppose
that's
truth is a great a a great centerpiece
of quaker thinking
wow
i think that's my answer for the moment
but you can come back if you want
well i want to give space to solid i
mean i feel like we're talking about
something
really sacred maybe you want to say
something solid
yeah actually i was i was wondering if
that that meaning was a
universal quaker practice or is it just
on your branch of of what you're
doing or participating in i i won't
speak for universal quaker practice
because there isn't really i mean
there are some there are some people
that use the quaker name
that are effectively like her
like many other protestant churches
you know that have a pastor and a
service but
but i think um
in france unfortunately there's not much
quakerism and
on the con there's not
a lot of eye either it's i don't know
why it's it's mainly anglophone
places um in africa there's apparently
quite a lot of
churches that go that are called quaker
but it's not necessarily our kind of
quakerism
um
so i'm not sure about the universality
um but i think within
i think within the the british quaker
tradition it's
it's quite common to have that kind of
sense
and that's the tradition you're part of
the british really
yes oh yes yes absolutely yes yes yes
yes
and and that meaning that you're talking
about that is that the crucial part of
the
what sort of meaning i mean can you just
tell me what you heard
of the non-hierarchic ministry where you
you steal the mind and and just anyone
can let it speak
is it is
that's the essence the essence of quaker
worship is
okay the silent meeting for the essence
of the silent meeting for worship is
indeed
that um there is no structure
there is no ritual there is simply
sitting in a circle
and waiting if and when
somebody is called to speak yeah
there are no prayers there is no songs
there is no
no and that's the only way you
your your tradition participate together
in communities yes okay oh wow yes
yes yes i mean that that's basically ev
ev every
in an active meeting that happens every
week i mean there's some
some smaller meetings you know it's less
frequent but
an active meeting like like this one in
lancaster
they hold an hour-long meeting for
worship every week
and then the other interesting thing of
course is that because there are no paid
ministers
the business has to be done everybody by
everybody collectively as well
so um so every month
there tends to be a a a meeting for
business and the interesting thing in
quakers is that we call it a meeting for
worship
for business so in others the business
is done
it is meant to be done i'm not saying it
always happens but the
the idea is that the business is done in
the same spirit
as the meeting for worship put aside
your own ego
yes you bring your contribution you say
what
your what you start with what your
starting point is your opinion if you
like
but then you leave it at that and
so for example there is a custom
of not speaking more than once to any
particular
point of business and what happens
what happens then is the clerk who is
just somebody who is basically
volunteering to
to actually to to to to to write the um
the minutes uh the the clerk then puts
together a minute and then
that's read out and then the question is
does this express
the sense of the meeting and the sense
of the meeting
is a little bit difficult to define but
basically what the clerk is trying to do
is the clerk is trying to
get a sense of what is the collective
what is there in the collective
consciousness what is the collective
will
the clerk is trying to express in words
what the
what the collective decision is not what
any particular individual
says and certainly not what they think
um
but uh what and and the collective
will appears as people
contribute as people add as people say
have you thought about this or how about
that and this is what
this is what my experience and that's my
experience
so i think that's another important
point about about quaker practice is
that it's not only the
meeting for worship which is which is
just completely open it's also the
meeting for worship for business where
you when you have
you have to look after the meeting house
you have to you know
do lots of practical things and those
things as well
get done in the same spirit yeah
i think there's something i really like
about
the way you do things which is the great
respect for
individual dignity that seems
just ensconced in the practice itself
that you just you can't take too many
steps forward
without respecting your sister or your
brother so to speak
i think that's that's right um
you know everybody has access to the
spirit
everybody has that seed that that of god
in them everybody has their own
light and
you cannot dismiss anybody i think
there's a
there's a famous story i don't know
whether it's true or not but um
not how true it is but uh the quakers in
pennsylvania you know when they were
meeting the native
the native uh indigenous people there
um i can't remember which way around it
was but there was a recognition
that oh yes that's what we do as well
you know and so
there is a very clear recognition that
um
[Music]
these people are equally in touch with
the spirit equally
um children of god if you like
and so that's one of the reasons why
quakers were as you probably know from
john woolman people quakers were leaders
in in the campaign against
slavery for example sadly speaking
some quakers were also slave owners but
but at least at least collectively
quakers got around to
uh being leaders in the abolition of
slavery
and um yeah equal and equality of
respect for
different races and so forth and indeed
and indeed
genders as well i mean like you know
quakers have
been very positive in the sense of like
you know there's no
there's no i mean like one of the sad
things about
um some christian sects is that you
still have this distinction between only
men are allowed to be priests
that's gone in a lot of um you know
there's there's some difference you know
that
men are special in a way that women
aren't what a load of nonsense
yeah i mean yeah but
that's how people have interpreted it
unfortunately
so so i think so that's one of the other
things i really like about about the
quaker
quaker tradition is that how they really
take equality seriously
oh absolutely
and as you say quality respect for each
individual
yeah and that's no small thing
i mean that's almost everything
and and and the opposite is also true
that the uh the disregard for the
dignity of others is the cause of many
long-standing strifes
in the world solid i hope i didn't just
not to speak yeah
please go ahead yeah
please i sold it i hope i didn't uh jump
on
uh where you were going by the way no
that's my last one
um one way to tie your own country
solid uh in with what uh
simon said something very powerful
earlier and i i wish
i got it exactly but when you were
talking simon about um
the profundity of what happens when you
are in
meeting and you're faced with your own
conscious
conscience excuse me it reminded me of
that
well well-known quote from blaise pascal
a frenchman who who said
you know something like i'm paraphrasing
but most of man's problems
come from his inability to sit quietly
in a room by himself
hmm
something to that
and that was even back then wasn't it
it's even worse now
oh yeah yeah totally
and i think i think that's one of the
things
which is worth mentioning about the
experience of quaker meeting for worship
which i do recommend by the way
if you haven't actually experienced the
live quaker meeting of worship
then when coronavirus allows do you know
um it's a ve the site the quality of
silence is a very accepting silence
yeah how can you and it's strange to say
the quality of the silence but
you know silence has a quality to it
different silences have quality to it
some silence is
a silence of fear
there is a silence which is the silence
of fear i dare not say anything
because if i say anything i will be
judged
criticized blamed and the quaker silence
is completely the opposite
quaker silence is a very accepting
silence it feels like
anybody really there is room for anybody
to speak there is no distinction as to
worthiness of
whether you're worthy or not to minister
everybody is assumed to be worthy of
ministry
to minister it's just a question of
whether you actually feel the call to
minister or not
and so just to go on just to go a bit
beyond pascal
and you know it's not just the ability
to sit in science with yourself
but it's also the ability to sit in
silence with
others in a circle
that's something that comes up in in
collective presence as well you know
that
um that from a purely secular point of
view you know there is a there is a
practice of being able to
not needing to jump in there
to give space to just to
to to listen without needing to respond
to
and to accept
a reflective silence and accepting
silence when when it feels right to do
that as well
because i think i think the opposite
too often somebody says something and
somebody will jump in and say no that's
that's wrong or no that's you know
i think differently well
no you don't want to do that you you
know
you you listen and even in quaker
circles there's this this tradition of
of you
um you
if if something doesn't speak to you
maybe it speaks to somebody else you
know so
maybe what you hear says that doesn't
make any sense to me but you don't know
it may be making a lot of sense to
somebody else
you might be speaking very personally to
so it's not for you to discount
something or to
undervalue or to put aside or to dismiss
something that somebody else says
that's that's not a good idea because
it's too often just mistaken
um and again based on your own
ego centered
structures your own way of thinking
[Music]
yes this doesn't make any sense to me
but hang on this is just me and
there are lots of other people that make
sense of the world in different ways
back to your original point julian about
meaning
um
i think people with no meaning people
who are really lost
i i discovered this when i was a student
actually um very interestingly
i i kind of came to discover this the
wrong word but
i kind of recognized this in myself
when i was a student in my student years
that
people that are very insecure and have
no meaning in their lives
they appreciate somebody telling them
what the meaning of life
is and that's where you get the kind of
evangelical position you know
oh feel lost hey we have the answers you
know
you just have to listen to us we tell
you the answers
but then you you grow a bit and you
think well hang on
we've all got answers to this and all
our answers are
potentially different we all come at
things from a different perspective
but then the really
um the really worthwhile
place to go from that is to listen
yes you have your answers at the moment
but if you listen hard if you listen
deeply
to what other people have to say then
[Music]
that deepens your own understanding i
think
oh and sometimes it challenges your own
understanding
sometimes you're stuck in a particular
world view sometimes you're stuck with a
particular model of how things work and
but when you really listen you think oh
okay maybe that's not right for
everybody maybe that's not the only way
of thinking about it
and uh it's one of the things that's in
this sort of set of related discord
groups that we're kind of part of it's
it's something that comes up quite a lot
this um this kind of talking across
the across the divide
and you know like
polarities polarization in society only
exists
only is maintained because people will
not actually listen
to people from the other side they get
dismissed before being listened to
and that's
one thing that we can do is we can
listen
respectfully respectfully doesn't quite
get it but
it's like respectfully we can listen
from the heart to
what other people are saying and
not just what they're saying but where
they're coming from what their meaning
what their what what the spirit is
behind what they're saying
and that can lead to insight into what
they are and also in
lead insight into to give us more
insight into where
where we could be as well something like
that
so much in what you said there's so many
things popping up for me
i'll just let solid have a go at first
no that's why you go ahead
so many things i think the the the thing
that emerges the most
simon out of listening to your um
[Music]
practice um
is that that expression that that is in
the old testament
uh the still small voice of god
ah yes elijah on mount carmel yes
no elijah not in my car elijah and no
it's somewhere else elijah yes i know
what he didn't mean yes
okay yeah yeah i don't know if that
factors in but it just comes through
loudly
i mean again excuse the expression
well it comes to very quietly maybe
but i mean it strikes me um i'm reminded
of that
and even to solids earlier point about
the um
the world we live in is so noisy the
media world
that we live in you know and and to your
point too
simon about um the appeal of the
let's say the proactive evangelical
message
um is that we are dunked
uh from childhood in
a non-stop messaging environment
that will not stop telling us do this
do that don't buy that
etc and we i i'm probably
getting a little bit into my personal
project by by going down that path
but the net effect of that
enormous apparatus especially for the
vulnerable
for you know i particularly care about
children who don't have
parents to protect them from it
is that you are just in your weaker
moments going to be taken up with one of
those messages
if you don't have a practice and this is
where hopefully what we're talking about
is useful into these communities
that we're trying to serve into uh
is you know encouraging the kinds of
practices where you do connect
to your inner light
because that is the only way um
forward you know one of the other i mean
there's two things i wanted to put out
there then i'll hand back over and one
one thing that really yeah please
excuse me i've just got to go to court
yeah
no problem but
so uh are you are you interesting in uh
bringing
collective princessing to uh the retinal
community
do you mean simon yeah or
you
[Music]
hang on no problem
so i i don't know anything about it
solid to be honest
uh okay it is something
which is um the province of
um simon's partner ria
she she she's
yeah fostering that practice okay yeah
yeah that's that's that sounds really
interesting i wonder if it could be done
like the the way we the way that this
community does thing
through zoom and discord and whatnot
yeah but
it's i know it seems that
being in the same place together would
be is
maybe a crucial part of the of the
practice though
yeah uh i don't want to speak to it too
much i think that
simon is clearly much more practiced
than i
am i'm used to being quiet on my own
yeah
i quite like it um but uh
the doing it as a practice together and
being quiet
sounds like a great idea yeah yeah yeah
okay
yeah a great idea
um
yeah i mean in in in my own um
in my own faith there is a way of doing
this
um which simon was talking to a little
bit earlier about the holy spirit and
that sort of thing
so i'm not sure if you you've had any
experience with that kind of thing but i
i i've had some practice what what
what we would say like listening
listening to the spirit or something
like that
and anyone by yourself is that a solo
practicer
uh yeah look i do i do that by myself uh
that's when i'm praying um
to me that's the mechanism by which
my prayers would be working so
in the christian sense the holy spirit
is is called the helper
i think that's the original greek word
it's the helper
there's a kind of agency that's outside
of yourself there
yeah but you know uh my earlier practice
was very much involved with other people
seeking to hear that i think it's very
much the same as
as that um uh what simon was
talking about waiting you know and yeah
have you had any experiences with that
yourself solid
with the oh no no no presidency
uh no i couldn't say no not really
yeah i know i don't have a christian
background at all
sure but i'm not
so but i'm quite interested in it though
i think because i
i think that uh it's so much part of our
of our
cultural background that it's it's those
i think those types are
of of practices uh could be much more
profound and and for for people i mean
for people from our culture
because people tend to go towards more
eastern practices
and and i'm so i'm just not quite sure
that
that because of their own eastern
cultural
metaphysics and whatnot i'm not sure
that it's actually appropriate for us
that much
oh right right right yeah
and i suppose in france you're kind of
surrounded by this
culture and architecture that's just
steeped in
christianity oh yeah yeah yeah yeah
yeah that's for sure so yeah i'm really
interested in trying to learn more about
christianity and and and prayers and
practices in the communities and so
that's jealous
i think his his quaker the quakers
practice of
of meaning is i mean yeah that's
very powerful yeah i agree yeah
yeah right and yeah
yeah i know where i think for sure it's
it's really
it always breaks my heart to when when
you see how
how to some degree how lost our culture
is when you hear about those practices
and
and just those communities it's really
sad that people people
i mean you can i can sense that people
are missing that and
they mostly i mean most of them really
don't they don't know that they're
missing such a
yeah powerful of stealing the mind and
being and being together silent and
you know those type of types of things
and it's it's so hard it seems so hard
to
to bring it about you know because yeah
how could you just start a
community and just start i guess you
have to at some point
yeah i i agree with you uh solid
i love what you're saying i mean it yeah
but it's so deeply valuable
and uh and at the same time for that
very reason
it is missing
i don't say that with an agenda i i i
genuinely feel like
um people are cutting themselves off
from
their own internal resources yeah um
and i'm sure that's exactly john
viveki's uh
whole appeal and that's why people like
what he's doing and
so oh yeah for sure yeah there is um
perhaps someone you'd also find helpful
um because i'm very conscious of
not trying to bias the conversation
toward christianity
that's not what this community is about
yeah
um i want to declare my own kind of
background and
and be clear about it but um
[Music]
there's no there's no message there's no
agenda to push there
but there is uh a fellow who i think
um you'd find helpful to listen to his
name's rupert sheldrake
and he's oh yeah yeah yeah sure i've
heard of him
okay so he's got that book um science
and spiritual practices
all right i've never read that though
well he he talks about seven spiritual
practices
um that
regardless i think of what religion
you're coming from
have this kind of positive scientific
if you will effect on you and i think
the one that sprung to mind when i'm
talking to you is
uh pilgrimage yeah well that's true yeah
that's very interesting
what is this actually something i've
been thinking about a lot going on a
on a because i love going on treks and
one night and
i think like a really monthly
really hard just one um i would be
really interested in that
you know that's really weird that you
would say that yeah
maybe check out what he's got to say on
on youtube but i think to
to start you off solid um the
interesting thing about rupert sheldrake
is that
he was an atheistic scientist
who who then converted back to
christianity
in a an indian ashram
which was run by a run by a benedictine
monk or something like that not
something like thomas merton or somebody
else
but um can i just say i i think i think
i better go
um i got the gas man here so
yeah so but lovely to talk to you both
so thank you
thank you simon uh is it okay yeah this
gets put on
to youtube by the discord sure i don't
think many people
watch it but yes no problem can i just
say
uh i really deeply thank you for your
willingness to look especially since you
don't know me from adam
and i just really deeply uh appreciate
you giving your attention in your time
yeah that's good thanks for asking
cheers bye now thank you
bye yeah so
i'm back to um sheldrake um so
yeah and he so he calls himself
what what's known as an atheist not as
in
an atheist but an atheist so it's like
we're an atheist now you're back to
theism something like that
and back to pilgrimage he's just saying
you know
um he realized how much in his own
culture
in um britain
there's just this you know really long
deep tradition of sacredness and
um
sacred yeah i think oh yeah sacred and
sick
sacred sides you know yeah yeah yeah
yeah uh
and so he he will you know go on these
pilgrimages to different cathedrals
around britain
and they just part of part of the
experience is probably just walking
through the countryside together
and enjoying the the land in which
you're living
yeah and
stopping at the different different
churches or whatnot and
and meeting the meeting the people and
uh and staying with them and talking
with them
i think that's such an important part as
well perhaps you're right yeah
yeah you don't know but i really like
the way he's going about it and
um as i say i mean um
you can approach it as a scientist and
look at it from that
lens in terms of your own inquiry
which would be helpful for some reason i
wanted to ask you
uh is your region where you're living
anywhere near
longadoc longer dock region
no no that's that's the opposite
actually i'm a
top top north and that longer dock is a
tough south uh west right okay
i'm not sure why i feel prompted to ask
you that question but
sorry that seems to be a region which is
very very deep
uh and it's got a deep and rich history
too i'm not sure
oh well i mean i don't know who said
that but uh
every and everywhere you walk in europe
you know it's just history history
everything that's pretty crazy man
that's pretty crazy
oh absolutely yeah yeah my mom comes
from
prague oh well yeah yeah so
yeah yeah yeah that's very beautiful too
it is and um the history there too
it's it's every every everywhere and
yeah
matters
it's it's really weird for like trying
to be present
of all the like every step you make
it's it's yeah it's like thousands of
years before you they were
people were stepping here and yeah it's
it's a really weird experience
yeah oh absolutely
i appreciate your uh you sort of you're
inquiring
mind about it you seem open-minded and
fair-minded which is great
it's a quality required
yeah i think most of the people seem
that way on the on the server to
actually uh it's a really neat community
i think and uh
i'm actually just new to it and and i
really
i really want to learn more of the
people here for sure
yeah i agree uh partly
the reason i wanted to do this today was
to foster
more of a sense of that i think
everybody's trying to work out
the protocol of you know
i feel a bit scared to share too much or
yeah maybe people aren't listening to me
uh or seeing what i'm giving and
um you know i think i went through all
those emotions and i'm sure other people
are as well yeah
yeah that's a good that was a good idea
have you been
have you been on the on the server for a
long time not really
um maybe a bit longer than a month or
more
um i've been following what john
viveki's done for about
a year probably ever since he did the
meaning crisis thing
yeah and it just was impossible to
ignore
um and
one of the areas that i
am feeling compelled about is the
religion that's not a religion idea
uh you know that's a really big idea
yeah trying to come to grips with it in
an honest way
yeah okay
[Music]
how about yourself what's your story a
little bit solid
well my story is kind of weird uh you
know i was i went to uh
i'm 22 years old so like four years ago
i
started college and uh really i i wasn't
i was in it i wasn't about any of this
at all and i went out i was just
kind of like just going through life
like regularly i guess like most people
not really thinking about anything but
and so when i came across
i i did so i just i just went to college
for started the year my first year in
geology
and uh because it's just because i had
to do something you know i was it was
it's really sad how
there's no no direction for for kids
around kids here and you expect them to
to make just such big choices for their
life like just
like you know then really think about it
it's really crazy and so i know i had i
know i was
i know i was kind of lost i guess
unconsciously to some degree because
and i mean i've been i like geology but
uh that's not really what i wanted to do
with my life or anything
and so when i for some reason i know why
i came across
uh some like conspiracy theories and
whatnot and that really
that really shook me like to to
because it was really directed towards
more kind of
the loss of spirituality in the world
and and like
how the government and is is kind of
like manipulating people tonight to not
think on their own and whatnot and so
that really
that really struck me because because at
the time i mean
i didn't have any critical thinking so
you know it was just
yeah i was so it was just really
powerful for me to to learn that you
could actually learn to think by
yourself
and and not just accept like how things
are and when
and so of course it
they put me in a weird position with
school and whatnot so i just
i just kind of stopped and and uh
and just started reading as much as i
could and getting informations
and get i got it i had to get a job and
so that's mostly what that's
kind of what i've been doing for the
last three years since the covet
it's just just yeah trying to learn
about stuff and and whatnot
and then yeah and then now uh i'm uh
because of the query i had to stop
working
because there were just yeah yeah
nothing stopped so now i've been
unemployed
and and so i've been thinking about
probably going back to school and get a
kind of degree in philosophy and when
i've been really interested in
philosophy
since uh yeah since learning oh yeah
because i mean
because the conspiracy kind of mindset
kind of went away after a while
it was just it was just yeah yeah
it was just uh
you know the uh how to say
like the the difference between like
being
yeah having the sense of having no
direction and
and not being able to like to think and
just accepting kind of things blindly
you know just going
going like like this kind of cultural
routine you know just kind of following
it without thinking about yourself
and just yeah this distinction it was
really really weird for me like i wasn't
expecting at all i really should be
kinda
strongly to to get on my own kind of
journey
yeah i appreciate you um sharing the
story so clearly
i mean did you find yourself going along
with those
uh conspiracy theories solid and at some
point you
struck something that seemed wrong or
uh well
i mean i i guess yeah i was i was kind
of i was really interested in it
and uh yeah i just
i i mean and i knew because because i uh
i guess i was lucky that it was
kind of kind of how presented in a way
that you have to
think that this is what you would come
to the conclusion if you were thinking
about yourself and so i really
that's really what like i
um i was oriented towards is like trying
to start to think about myself and so of
course after a while
when you get more information you
realize it's yeah they have a
conspiracy i mean most conspiracy
theorists do they have their own
like dogmas and why not so uh they're
not
so it's kind of so it's kind of it's
kind of weird thing then i really
i mean yeah it's that it's like like any
dogma really
right like it's like it's like putting
blinders on you know you see all the
you see all the or you may i mean you're
the one making the connections basically
between all those where where things are
now
okay so yeah yeah yeah so so you're
um you're reading for yourself you're
kind of uh
arming yourself to discern truth from
falsity
the true from the false yeah yeah
it reminds me of uh noam chomsky you
know much about
i don't know i know i know him but i
don't know much about him
yeah i like chomsky a lot he um
back in the 1960s i think this is
permanent to what we're
what we're talking about he he wrote a
book called manufacturing consent
and and the manufacturing consent was
all about how
media and different um
institutions like that have an effect on
you but the point i'm trying to make was
really what his solution was
which i think the way he put it was uh
we need to teach ourselves intellectual
self-defense
yeah that's pretty good
yeah so it was really powerful for me
from the get-go how
how culture was lacking that for such a
bit in such a big way
and then and then as i go deep as i get
deeper with
different like turning into different
philosophies in young and
and more eastern philosophy and and
peterson and viveki
then really the add more is it became
more i became oriented towards
the spiritual religious side that that
we're missing
right and so that's that's what i'm
really interested in now right now
yeah and so that's yeah and i agree that
i think the
red noise is really
it seems crazy like when i think about
it sometimes it seems really crazy like
like how could you go about creating a
new religion
which is not a religion but yeah but
yeah you see what i mean
but i think this is probably the way to
go because i don't see really any
any different way that things could i
mean yeah i don't know
i don't know if if there's any other
solution real
hmm i i'm being really careful about
the religion that's not a religion um i
i believe john vivek is acting in
in really good faith about it i think
the best
the best frame that i can put it in for
myself is that
his thesis is well
the steady decline of religion over the
centuries
led to the rise of
political ideologies which themselves
sort of yielded results which were even
more horrific
and so he's sort of proposing what we
need to do is
come to neither this nor that if you
know what i mean
yeah um as far as i understand it solid
that's
that's the starting point where he's
coming from
but you know maybe people watching this
in the community will
correct me um but i'll probably i won't
say too much about it until i'm more
confident
i know what utility it might have
even for christians i was talking with
brett you know who
who runs the administration of the
server
yeah and we had a quick chat about it
and
um i i think we
tended to agree that maybe one of the
benefits of having something like this
religion that's not a religion would be
to improve
the quality of existing religions anyway
because place yeah yeah i know
yeah that's very interesting i never
thought about that because yeah
it makes a lot of sense to me because
if if say you're a christian solid and
you're living in whatever 1920 or
something like that
you're still going to be believing in
evolution probably
and the theory of gravity and has
nothing to do with
what your faith belief is uh
on its own you know your faith belief is
going to be informed by
a certain inner uh
sense of what fits for you and that sort
of thing
i tend to put this religion that's not a
religion in that category which is it's
going to be
enormously informed by
cognitive science and philosophy and
you know john vivek is moral you know
undoubtedly
and if a
buddhist or a
hindu takes up the good sides of those
things and that helps them to practice
their religion
or our religion in a more
um beneficial way than good
then good yeah
i think that's the most the best way i
can view
what it's for
okay yeah sure yeah well well
i mean the way i saw it was that
was that the point would be to to like
try to get back
like i mean to me that's the way i
understood it is that
the point would be to to to get back the
what religion did but like in a new you
know new kind of
scientifically updated modern way i
think
yeah yeah and so
because yeah because i mean oh our whole
culture uh the whole culture used to be
just keeping religion and the
communities and we wanna and that's yeah
we definitely that's that
i think and uh and so and uh yeah
for sure i mean to me it makes sense
that it's a big part of what's going on
right now is
just being so so kind of divided and
lasting
and yeah right
absolutely yeah yeah i think you're
raising some good questions and i'm
going to have to go in about five
minutes
yeah but i i think it's a good place for
us to
to to finish up because of all the
questions that have to do with it
so what you said like i think what you
said sounds right from what i've
understood as well which is john viveki
is trying to reverse engineer religion
yeah the same way that he reverse
engineered
enlightenment and god knows i learned a
ton
by that process but by the same token
i'm religious so what am i going to do
is is the excuse me is the um
is the god of the religion that is not a
religion
non-theism
as far as i can tell that might be the
case um
[Music]
and for me like to be honest non-theism
doesn't worry me at all
um my own experience of god when i see
god
is very non-theistic it's like there's
no words
um it shatters all of my
kind of mental models of everything
it's just like a big old relaxed restful
nothing so if that's non-theism not a
problem
i you know that's okay with me
um but you know there's a lot of
you know when you're religious um
depending on how you go about it
okay it's you're making real vows to god
you're saying like i need your help i
[Music]
i'm asking for your help and
and you're sort of learning about it and
you're going okay what's required of me
so that i can help myself to move
forward
and those sorts of things and i can
speak personally you know
i meant that when i said it and i feel
grateful for it
um so this kind of project the religion
that's not a religion stirs up those
kinds of
deeply held things and i'm wrestling
with it
and as i said to one of the other guys
on the server i can't remember who it
was
jarvis jarvis from tasmania here in
australia
i said i feel like i'm about a year away
from really
having some firm position on on what's
going on there
yeah yeah yeah for sure i can i can
understand
oh yeah well okay i if it's all right
with you i'm gonna
stop the recording and um finish up on
my end
anything you wanted to add on before we
stop yeah i'm sure that was a
i mean thank you for sending that out
that was that was quite interesting and
uh
yeah and simon yes and i was pretty
he was i mean he had really powerful
things